<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" type="xml-dtd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cesarvallejo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">César Vallejo</title>
                <author>Roque Dalton</author>
                <editor role= "translator" sameAs="#hsm">Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                <editor role= "translator" xml:id="jg">James Graham</editor>
                      <editor role= "translator">Jonathan Cohen</editor>
                       <editor role= "translator">Ralph Nelson</editor>
                        <editor role= "translator">Paul Pines</editor>
                         <editor role= "translator">David Unger</editor>
                <editor role="editor" xml:id="hsm">Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                <editor role="digital-edition-editor" xml:id="ib">Isabella Baker</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding</resp>
                    <persName resp="#ib">Isabella Baker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Boston College</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>Fall 2024</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Isabella Baker</authority>
                <availability>
                    <p>Licensed under a
                        <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>
                        (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit Isabella Baker. Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item should be sought by the original publisher.
                    </p>
                </availability>
                <idno>cesarvallejo</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="editorial">I have chosen my definition and categorization of “marxist rhetoric” based on James Martin's 2022 article “Marx's Rhetoric,”
                    featured in the Goldsmiths Research online repository. I focus on his detailed explanation of the rhetoric of criticism, dynamics of class
                    politics, and rhetoric of critical political economy. I often choose to mark phrases that read as “call to actions,” as Martin claims that 
                    Marx sought to urge the working class to become forces of social and political change. I also zone in on themes of martyrdom, that seem to 
                    align themselves with critiquing the governing classes while lauding the sacrifices of the lower (or change-making) classes.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Roque Dalton</author>
                    <editor>Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                    <editor role= "translator">Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                     <editor role= "translator">James Graham</editor>
                      <editor role= "translator">Jonathan Cohen</editor>
                       <editor role= "translator">Ralph Nelson</editor>
                        <editor role= "translator">Paul Pines</editor>
                         <editor role= "translator">David Unger</editor>
                    <date when="1996-09">September 1996</date>
                    <title>Small Hours of the Night: Selected Poems of Roque Dalton</title>
                    <idno type="isbn">9781880684351</idno>
                    <publisher>Northwestern University Press</publisher>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of this translated editions of Dalton's poems.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Roque Dalton</author>
                    <date when="2015">2015</date>
                    <title>El Turno del Ofendido</title>
                    <idno type="isbn">9781925019742</idno>
                    <publisher>Ocean Sur</publisher>
                    <note type="project">The Spanish text does not appear in this file, but is available as a PDF on the website.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
           <change who="#ib" when="2024-10-28">Created document and added basic structural TEI.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="cesar-vallejo-english.pdf"/>
            <div1 type="poem">
               
                <head type="main-authorial"><persName>CÉSAR VALLEJO</persName></head> 
            
                <lg type="stanza">
                
                    <l>This dead body bursting into flower </l>
                    <l>—good breeding </l>
                    <l>raises its knife-edge—</l>
                    <l>this body not yet introduced to me </l>
                    <l>better than when it lived <interp type="marxist-rhetoric">yields to death itself </interp><ptr target="#no1"/></l>
                    <l>it waves its petals to the seeds of love</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l>This dead body who would have imagined it </l>
                    <l><interp type="marxist-rhetoric">defending its cup of storms </interp><ptr target="#no2"/></l>
                    <l>visited by blind circus butterflies </l>
                    <l>its huge pores dead </l>
                    <l>its old smokes dead from his sitting there </l>
                    <l>with only its dead-looking roots alive </l>
                    <l>prompt with the word it keeps to itself </l>
                    <l>its eternal slippery hand still trembling </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l>This dead body that contradicts me </l>
                    <l>growing shoulder to shoulder with the language </l>
                    <l>of a <interp type="marxist-rhetoric">just calamity that crackles </interp><ptr target="#no3"/></l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l>This dead body of dry water </l>
                    <l>this critically ill </l>
                    <l>dead body whose bones are guests </l>
                    <l>comes in runs its fingers over its flags </l>
                    <l><interp type="marxist-rhetoric">interrogates its interrogators</interp><ptr target="#no4"/></l>
                    <l>this body gives with all its heart the only thing it owns </l>
                    <l>it wept it comes back and goes away weeping </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l>Somewhere in the world his tombstone breathes</l>
                    <l>under the <interp type="marxist-rhetoric">solemn weight</interp><ptr target="#no5"/> of the name he gave life to </l>
                    <l>one day he said things that will always last </l>
                    <l>the world is much heavier since his death </l>
                    </lg>
              <note type="editorial" target="#hsm"> [HSM] </note>
            </div1>
            <note xml:id="no1">"Yielding" to death connotes the finale of a battle of survival. Dalton fought on behalf of the working class
             and was exiled for his alleged traitorous behavior against the Salvadoran government. The sentiment of being willing to die (for 
             an anti-capitalist cause) is characterized as honorable, positively attributing Marxist motives.
              </note>
            <note xml:id="no2">The "cup of storms" may refer to an individualized, controlled rage against injustice (confined, to a degree). 
            "Defending" and thus, acting on this individualized, violent rage against injustice is emotionally characteristic of a Marxist "urging" towards 
            immediate political and social change </note>
            <note xml:id="no3">Calamity can refer to any notion of disaster, but the notions of a "just" calamity implies that disaster was warranted.
            Disaster negatively affects populations, but for Marxists, disaster enacted on oppressors may seem justifiable. Such calamity, in turn,
            "crackles" with the opportunity for an overturning of power.</note>
            <note xml:id="no4">Interrogation appears most often in the context of a criminal case, where serving justice is the overarching goal. However, 
            Dalton asks us, in Marxist fashion, to questions those who question us. In other words, one must be critical about the agents that enact social and 
            political order.</note>
            <note xml:id="no5">This solemn weight, externally referring to a revered literary figure, may also refer to the burden that every Marxist 
            revolutionary carries to constantly question the status quo.</note>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>