<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> 
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" type="xml-dtd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="megalomania">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Megalomania</title>
                <author>Roque Dalton</author>
                <editor role="translator" sameAs="#hsm">Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                <editor role="translator" xml:id="jg">James Graham</editor>
                      <editor role="translator">Jonathan Cohen</editor>
                       <editor role="translator">Ralph Nelson</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Paul Pines</editor>
                         <editor role="translator">David Unger</editor>
                <editor role="editor" xml:id="hsm">Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                <editor role="digital-edition-editor" xml:id="ib">Isabella Baker</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoding</resp>
                    <persName resp="#ib">Isabella Baker</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Boston College</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>Fall 2024</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Isabella Baker</authority>
                <availability>
                    <p>Licensed under a
                        <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref>
                        (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of the material should credit Isabella Baker. Permission to reproduce the graphic images of the original item should be sought by the original publisher.
                    </p>
                </availability>
                <idno>megalomania</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="editorial">I have chosen my definition and categorization of “marxist rhetoric” based on James Martin's 2022 article “Marx's Rhetoric,”
                    featured in the Goldsmiths Research online repository. I focus on his detailed explanation of the rhetoric of criticism, dynamics of class
                    politics, and rhetoric of critical political economy. I often choose to mark phrases that read as “call to actions,” as Martin claims that 
                    Marx sought to urge the working class to become forces of social and political change. I also zone in on themes of martyrdom, that seem to 
                    align themselves with critiquing the governing classes while lauding the sacrifices of the lower (or change-making) classes.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Roque Dalton</author>
                    <editor>Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                    <editor role="translator">Hardie St. Martin</editor>
                     <editor role="translator">James Graham</editor>
                      <editor role="translator">Jonathan Cohen</editor>
                       <editor role="translator">Ralph Nelson</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Paul Pines</editor>
                         <editor role="translator">David Unger</editor>
                    <date when="1996-09">September 1996</date>
                    <title>Small Hours of the Night: Selected Poems of Roque Dalton</title>
                    <idno type="isbn">9781880684351</idno>
                    <publisher>Northwestern University Press</publisher>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of this translated editions of Dalton's poems.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Roque Dalton</author>
                    <date when="2015">2015</date>
                    <title>El Turno del Ofendido</title>
                    <idno type="isbn">9781925019742</idno>
                    <publisher>Ocean Sur</publisher>
                    <note type="project">The Spanish text does not appear in this file, but is available as a PDF on the website.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ib" when="2024-10-28">Created document and added basic structural TEI.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="megalomania-english.pdf"/>
            <div1 type="poem">
               
                <head type="main-authorial">MEGALOMANIA</head>
            
                <lg type="stanza">
                
                    <l>Frederick II was emperor of the <interp type="marxist-rhetoric">high-and-mighty</interp><ptr target="#no1"/>Germans and yet </l>
                    <l><interp type="marxist-rhetoric">he was excommunicated by the Pope</interp><ptr target="#no2"/></l>
                    <l>because he made the study of medicine a requisite for doctors </l>
                    <l>before they could prescribe infusions for a fee </l>
                    <l>or cut off flesh from a person's flesh. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l><interp type="marxist-rhetoric">Miguel Servet was excommunicated shortly before</interp><ptr target="#no3"/></l> 
                    <l>they reduced him to ashes: </l>
                    <l>they say this was to speed it up for him</l> 
                    <l>to go on discussing the advanced sciences in restful eternity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l>Martin Lutherbbelieved God the Father's divine liver acted up </l>
                    <l>whenever he looked through the clouds and saw fat priests </l>
                    <l>running around </l> <!--justify right-->
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l><interp type="marxist-rhetoric">city neighborhoods getting rich</interp><ptr target="#no4"/> from the sale of indulgences </l>
                    <l>paid in hardcash, </l> <!--justify right-->
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l><interp type="marxist-rhetoric">He was thrown out of the Church</interp><ptr target="#no5"/>for defending God's liver</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg>
                    <l>Thin, puny, with wary eye and down-trodden look, </l>
                    <l>I'd have to perform marvelous actions like theirs </l>
                    <l>to be also thrown out of the Church </l>
                    <l>and save my artless vanity forever. </l>
                    </lg>
              <note type="editorial" target="#hsm"> [HSM] </note>
            </div1>
            <note xml:id="no1">Marx often critiqued class issues, namely to do with property relations. Dalton refers to the "high and mighty"
            Germans, who were a foremost military and world power during Frederick II's reign. Dalton here recognizes the downfall of powerful
            structures, even ones on a national scale,like the Catholic church. He also betrays a level of atheism inherent in Marxism as he 
            criticized the Pope's dictator-like power to abide by religion over science.  </note>
            <note xml:id="no2">Dalton seems to be laying out the consequences for class/political hierarchies. Power structures do not easily
            allow a change of the status quo, even if that change is clearly for the better of the masses.</note>
            <note xml:id="no3">Another instance of a significant member of the "logical" sciences, creating something to better the masses,
            and being punished for it.</note>
            <note xml:id="no4">This is another example of class politics rhetoric, specifically referring to areas near cities that profit off
            urban resources and centrality, without engaging with the downfalls and poverties of urban life. </note>
            <note xml:id="no5">Another appeal against organized religion in comparison to his list of martyrs..</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>